So I'm an independent researcher.
My interests are in sort
of theoretical approaches to intersections
of art and technology, generally speaking,
and in continental philosophy.
But the paper today
is about electronic literature
and AI data work,
and it is based on my personal experience
of working as a transcriber
for AI projects
between 2023 and 2025,
in a business process outsourcing company
located in Eastern Europe.
So in the form that I experienced
it, transcription for AI projects
consisted of listening to audio recordings
provided by the client,
which is a major tech company
whose name cannot be mentioned
because of non-disclosure agreements,
and either transcribing those audio
recordings from scratch or correcting
an AI generated transcription.
The recordings are gathered
from users of digital devices,
many of whom appear to be unaware
of actually being recorded.
So my argument today
is that the stream of audio recordings
constitutes an impressive piece
of electronic literature,
despite the fact that it is not intended
as such.
An extraordinary cut up literary
composition of uncreative writing
made up of fragments of daily life,
often caught unawares,
combined with moments of musique concrète
from background noises to glitches
in the recording process, and so on.
I propose that the
event that makes the difference between
the audio recordings as a raw material
exploited in the industrial production
of so-called artificial intelligence
and the same audio recordings
as a piece of literature,
is the creation by transcribers
of what I call imaginary artworks.
And I'll tell you a bit
more what I mean by that.
So this paper aims to provide
the starting point for understanding
this concealed,
unintended piece of electronic literature
and the imaginary artworks
that I claim are associated with it.
Now, because of the imperative
of non-disclosure
that governs AI data work.
I cannot reveal any exact details
about the context
of the transcription work,
nor about the audio recordings themselves.
And I take this prohibition
to be actually a very inciting
and fertile ground
for the topic of this paper.
In fact, all of you already know enough
about the subject
in order to be able to glitch
this logic of enclosure
through some very simple
exercises of imagination.
What was I transcribing?
Well, everything that you can imagine
a user saying towards a device with voice
recognition capabilities,
or more exactly in the presence
of such a device, given
the fact that recording can be
unintentionally triggered.
And you know this
because of whistleblower articles
that were already published in the press.
And these are some examples from 2019
that I'm aware of,
but there are probably many others since.
And you also know it
because you are presumably agreeing
to this in the terms and conditions
of your applications on your smartphones.
Given the fact that you can be recorded
just as well by your own devices
as by the devices of other users,
it is only a small logical step
to realize that because of the general
uptake in our societies
of such digital technologies
with voice recognition capabilities,
you could be recorded at any moment,
intentionally or not, by
the device is owned by your neighbor,
by the policeman harassing you,
by the doctor's office, the company
that provides your medical supplies,
your lawyer, the phone company,
the supermarket tech support company,
and so on.
And the sample of all of this does feed
into the electronic piece of uncreative
writing that transcribers are witnessing
on a daily basis behind closed doors.
Now, in terms of format,
the length of the audio recordings ranges
from all the way from a few seconds
long, and such recordings are transcribed
in their hundreds or thousands per day
by each transcriber to instances
that are over an hour long,
which can require multiple work days
on the same audio recording.
The order of the recordings
seems to be random from the transcriber’s
perspective, but they are grouped
in so-called projects that give them
a certain degree of consistency,
both in terms of format and content.
Moreover, many recordings
appear in the data set multiple times.
Presumably, this happens
in order to ensure consistency across
multiple transcriptions.
Hence, for the transcriber,
an approximate interwoven
textual structure is slowly contoured,
punctuated by repetitions and callbacks,
a loose structure that encourages
a creative spectator engagement.
Despite oneself, one starts building up
meaningful if imaginary connections,
narrative, poetic, musical,
or otherwise, between the recordings
during the transcription work,
probably due to the excruciating boredom
of just performing the same robotic tasks
again and again, imagination
tends to take over
you want it or not, and combines
the recordings between them
and with fragments
of personal experience and memories
into these complex, surreal compositions.
Audio, visual, haptic and so on.
Inspired by the imaginary music
of composer Octavian Nemescu,
I suggest understanding
such imaginary compositions
that exist only for a very brief moment
in the imagination of transcribers
as artworks in their own right,
despite the fact that they remain
singular, personal,
unshakable experiences.
So let me give you a bit of an idea
of what imaginary music is in order to
understand what I'm driving it.
Nemescu started working with this idea
of imaginary music around 1974, 1975,
and for him, it is a musical genre
characterized by the fact that it is
radically anti spectacular,
being performed by each spectator
in their own imagination.
A piece of imaginary music
is a guided exercise of imagination
that starts with a score written
by the composer, oftentimes
using experimental
and conventional notation,
and you have fragments of such a score
on the screen.
But it is then the task of the spectator
to study to the best of their ability,
the score, to rehearse it actually,
and to perform it in their imagination
as best as they can.
There is no exterior trace
of the performance.
For Nemescu, imaginary music constitutes
an interior ritual that destabilizes
societal paradigms
based on the spectacle, and proposes
new ways for the individual to connect
and engage with their environments.
So I advocate for thinking
about the imaginary compositions
that emerge for transcribers
during the labor process as artworks
similar to the pieces of imaginary music
performed by spectators.
The starting point,
though, for these artworks, is not a score
written by a composer or an artist,
but this stream of audio recordings
of everyday life caught unawares.
So imagine, for example, a project
that is an extensive
set of audio recordings
with a certain degree of consistency
that transcribers will engage
with for multiple days in a row
and sometimes weeks, often weeks
and sometimes even months.
So imagine a project that contains, say,
10% recordings related to pornography
and just as much related to prayers,
which in my experience is pretty usual.
Some of these audio recordings
are spread over multiple audio
tracks,
fragmented and repeated multiple times.
This text texture, with its loose,
interwoven threads that cut across two
highly contested areas of contemporary
cultures, pornography and prayers,
offers a very fertile ground for sense
making, driven
maybe by the power of the false.
Whereby the power of the false,
inspired by Deleuze’s concept,
I simply understand this proliferation
of heterogeneous senses
upon the non-linear intermission of texts.
This non-linear cut ups of daily life.
Incidentally, such falsifications
or fabrications, I believe,
seem to constitute
some of the most truthful representations
of life and death
in contemporary digital cultures.
No other artists that I'm aware of,
or literature piece for that matter,
proves either the technological
and financial capacity or indeed
the ethical irresponsibility to offer its
spectators such an overwhelming boring.
Paradoxically,
at the same time, exhilarating patchwork
of intimate moments of
daily life caught unawares,
that are offered
as the pieces of a fragmentary
and ambiguous puzzle that is continuously
constructed and deconstructed
by the spectator’s/worker’s imagination.
So these streams of content,
in my opinion,
that AI data workers
face on a daily basis, constitute
some of the most intriguing masterpieces
of contemporary art and literature
in the second and third
decades of the 21st century,
and the fact that they are available
only to AI data workers
and inaccessible to art institutions
and their traditional publics,
I think, should not stop us
from recognizing and valuing them as such.
Now I'll get to my conclusion.
But instead of a conclusion,
I want to show you half a joke,
half serious, a score of sorts.
This time for a piece of imaginary
electronic literature
instead of a piece of imaginary music.
And I invite each of you to perform it
whenever you want, in your own time,
when you find it convenient, following
the instructions as closely as possible.
Now there is a trigger warning.
There is some mild explicit slang words
in the piece, and it does engage
with themes of death and sexuality. So
the piece
is called “How to Say in Russian: ‘Hey
Kevin, you're a dick.’”
It is to be performed
in a crowded public space of your choice.
First movement recommended time
between 3 and 5 minutes.
Remember instances of voice recording
software that you have used lately?
For example, do you have any smart home
assistant devices?
Do you use voice search on your smartphone
speech to text on your keyboard?
Does your doctor have a phone
answering machine?
What about your lawyer?
Have you contacted any customer
service lines lately?
Have you used any translation
devices with voice recognition
on your smartphone, etc.?
And try to remember some of the things
that you said in the presence
of digital devices
with such voice recognition software.
Second movement,
recommended time between 5 and 10 minutes.
Imagine what your parents,
what your children, your friends,
your neighbors, your colleagues say
in the presence of such devices.
Don't be shy.
Imagine what they are
whispering under the blankets
and what they are
screaming in the public square.
Imagine what they are saying
on the hospital bed, in the pub
or in the classroom.
Third movement.
No time limit.
I will finish in just a second.
Look around
you and choose a random person.
Imagine them being happy.
Imagine them being confused and angry.
Imagine them crying.
Imagine them masturbating and having sex.
Imagine them being excited.
Imagine them being bored.
Imagine them being scared.
Imagine them suffering and dying.
Imagine them in their tedious daily
routines.
And imagine
all the fragments that the digital devices
are capturing from all of this.
Not only what is said,
but the unintelligible sounds
and the acoustic backgrounds,
the breathing in and out,
the musicality of the voice,
the whispers, the screams, the coughing,
spitting, grunting,
snoring, panting and what have you.
Imagine the background TV noises, the car
engines, the rhythmic clicks
and clocks of unknown devices,
the computer games, shopping centers,
hospitals, the crowds, the voice
robots, the toilets flushing, doors
opening and closing, songbirds, rain,
traffic jams, and everything that
there are actually no words to describe.
Fourth movement.
Forget it all now.
If you go through this piece,
you will have a pretty good idea
of what transcribers are listening to
when they are doing the work of audio
transcription for AI projects.
I will finish here, but before stopping,
I just want 30 more seconds for a
quick note.
I find it very important to mention this
every time when I talk about this topic.
In academic contexts,
there is a growing academic literature
that insists on the exploitation
of cheap labor in AI data work.
I'm sure that you are all aware of that
and in general lines.
I subscribe to many of the arguments
made in this sense.
In my experience, though,
and I don't want to generalize.
I'm referring strictly to my experience,
and I want to mention this
the exploitative practices
that I encountered
while working as a transcriber in a video
were definitely not as pronounced as those
that I encountered as a PhD researcher
for four years
and as a sessional teaching staff
for a couple of semesters
at a top university.
And with that, I will finish. Thank you.